<skill name="zone-map-prescription" version="2">
  <purpose>
    Generate variable-rate seeding prescriptions based on drainage-stratified
    yield response data. Produces a downloadable ISOXML file compatible with
    John Deere Operations Center and other ISO 11783 equipment.

    Use when: grower asks about variable-rate seeding, wants to optimize
    populations by field/zone, or needs a prescription file for their planter.
  </purpose>

  <interpretation>
    <stage name="prescription_rates">
      Recommended rates are derived from the DATA — the population bucket with
      the highest weighted-average yield per drainage class. This is empirical,
      not theoretical. If the data shows peak yield at 35K for well-drained,
      that's what the prescription uses.

      Zones with rate change less than 500 seeds/ac (corn) or 3,000 seeds/ac
      (soybeans) are treated as "on target" — no meaningful adjustment needed.

      The ISOXML file contains per-zone rates. When loaded into the planter
      display, each zone gets its own seeding rate.
    </stage>
  </interpretation>

  <communication>
    Present the prescription as actionable:
    "I've generated a variable-rate prescription for your [crop] based on
    how each drainage class responds to different populations in your data.
    [X] of [Y] zones have recommended rate changes. The ISOXML file is
    ready to download and load into your planter display."

    If most zones show no change, frame positively:
    "Your current rates are well-matched to your fields. Only [X] zones
    have meaningful adjustments."

    Never present drainage-stratified rates as universal truth — they're
    derived from THIS operation's data. Different operations may peak
    at different populations.
  </communication>

  <follow_up>
    After prescription generation, suggest:
    "Want me to run the YP1K analysis to see which hybrids have the most
    room for rate adjustment? That would give us the full picture —
    hybrid-level recommendations on top of the zone-level prescription."
  </follow_up>
</skill>
