<skill name="yp1k-emergence-investigation" version="1">

  <purpose>
    Investigate emergence gaps flagged by the YP1K Stage 1 diagnostic. This plan fires when
    the main YP1K skill identifies a critical emergence gap and the pattern is planter_issue
    or mixed. It provides the detailed breakdown — which fields, which hybrids, which drainage
    conditions, and whether planting speed contributed — needed to give the grower a concrete
    next step.

    The goal of this investigation is not to replace the YP1K rate analysis. It is to answer
    the question: is this a planter-wide problem, a hybrid-specific problem, or a field-condition
    problem? The answer determines what the grower should do before next season.
  </purpose>

  <interpretation>

    <section name="pattern-first">
      Always start with the gap_result pattern from the analyze step. This is the highest-level
      finding and determines how to frame everything else.

      planter_issue (more than 80% of fields affected, gap consistent across all hybrids):
        The planter is not delivering seeds as commanded. The gap is not selective — it affects
        all hybrids roughly equally across all fields. This is a mechanical or calibration
        problem, not a seed or environment problem. Root causes include meter calibration drift,
        mechanical wear in seed disk or finger pickup, air pressure problems in pneumatic meters,
        seed tube wear causing seed bounce and skip, or row unit bounce from operating at the
        wrong speed for the planter type.

      mixed (30 to 80% of fields affected, gap selective across hybrids or fields):
        Some hybrids, varieties, or fields are affected but not all. This is a seed-environment
        mismatch pattern. Likely causes include specific hybrids with harder seed coats that
        perform poorly in cold or wet soils, specific fields with crusting or heavy residue,
        or seed treatment interaction with cool soils (fungicide packages vary in cold-soil
        efficacy). Identify which hybrids and fields are affected versus unaffected.

      localized (fewer than 30% of fields affected):
        Most of the data is valid. The affected zones likely have a field-specific explanation.
        This sub-plan normally does not fire for localized patterns — if it does, focus on the
        specific outlier fields and look for field-condition explanations.
    </section>

    <section name="hybrid-dimension">
      Examine the gap_by_hybrid table. The key question: is the gap spread uniformly across
      all hybrids, or is one hybrid driving the problem?

      If gap is uniform across all hybrids (standard deviation small relative to mean):
        This is a planter-wide signal. The equipment or operating conditions are the cause,
        not anything hybrid-specific. Tell the grower: "The gap is consistent across all your
        hybrids, which rules out seed performance as the cause."

      If one or two hybrids have much higher gaps than others:
        This is a hybrid-specific signal. The planter is likely working correctly — these
        specific hybrids are not performing as well in your planting conditions. Tell the grower
        which hybrids are affected and frame it as a seed-environment interaction to investigate.
        Ask whether those hybrids were planted in different field conditions, on different dates,
        or with different seed treatments.

      If all hybrids have elevated gaps but the magnitude varies:
        Mixed signal. The planter may have a baseline delivery problem AND some hybrids are
        more sensitive than others. Present both dimensions.
    </section>

    <section name="field-and-drainage-dimension">
      Examine gap_by_field and gap_by_drainage. These reveal whether the problem is spatially
      or environmentally concentrated.

      If the worst-gap fields share a drainage class:
        Cold, wet, or poorly drained soils commonly cause worse emergence. Early-planted fields
        in cold conditions are especially prone. Tell the grower: "The fields with the worst
        emergence share [drainage class] drainage. Cold, wet conditions at planting can suppress
        emergence in these soil types."

      If the worst-gap fields are geographically clustered or share a field characteristic:
        Look for a local explanation: tile failure, heavy residue mat, compaction layer. These
        are field-specific conditions and do not indict the planter or the seed.

      If gaps are uniformly bad across all drainage classes and field types:
        Reinforces the planter-issue pattern. No environmental clustering means the problem
        is not soil or weather driven — it is mechanical.
    </section>

    <section name="planting-speed">
      If planting speed data is available, examine the speed_summary output carefully before
      interpreting it. The correct interpretation depends on the planter type.

      For operations using high-speed planter technology (Precision Planting SpeedTube, Deere
      ExactEmerge, or similar hydraulic downforce systems):
        These planters are engineered to perform at their designed operating speed, typically
        5.5 to 7 or more miles per hour. Their hydraulic downforce systems continuously adjust
        to maintain consistent seed-to-soil contact. At very slow speeds, these systems can
        over-react to minor terrain variations, paradoxically reducing seed placement consistency.
        If the data shows that lower speeds produced worse emergence, this is consistent with
        high-speed planter behavior — planting too slowly on these machines degrades performance.
        Tell the grower: "For high-speed planter technology, operating below the designed speed
        can actually hurt emergence because the downforce control system over-corrects at slow
        speeds. If these fields were planted at [speed] mph, that may be contributing to the gap."

      For operations using conventional planters (without high-speed technology):
        Traditional agronomic wisdom applies: slower is better, especially above 5 mph. On
        conventional planters, higher speeds degrade seed spacing and depth uniformity.
        If the data shows worse emergence at higher speeds, this is the expected pattern.
        Do not generalize high-speed planter data to conventional equipment.

      If planter type is unknown:
        Present the speed data without a directional interpretation. Ask the grower what
        planter they use before concluding anything about speed effects.

      If no planting speed data is available:
        Note the absence and ask the grower whether they have records of operating speed for
        the affected fields. Speed data can be a key diagnostic for emergence problems.
    </section>

  </interpretation>

  <communication>
    This plan fires because a serious emergence problem was found. The grower may not know
    the severity. Be direct and specific from the start.

    Lead with the numbers: "Across your [crop_type] fields in [year], we are seeing an
    emergence gap of [X,XXX] seeds/acre on average — that is [Normal/Minor/Warning/Critical]."

    Name the pattern immediately: "The pattern is consistent across all your hybrids, which
    points to a planter delivery problem" OR "The gap is concentrated in [specific hybrids
    or fields], which suggests a seed-environment interaction."

    Explain the implication: "If we adjusted seeding rates based on YP1K right now, we would
    be building recommendations on an emerged stand that does not reflect what was planted.
    Any rate increase would go through the same planter at the same reduced delivery rate.
    The right move is to fix the root cause first, then re-run the YP1K analysis."

    Give the grower a concrete next step. Do not end with "investigate the planter."
    Say specifically: "I would recommend getting the planter meter calibrated and the seed
    disk inspected before next season" OR "Check whether [specific hybrid] was planted in
    different conditions — soil temperature, residue cover, or seed treatment differences
    may explain the gap for that variety specifically."

    If planting speed data shows a possible speed contribution, ask the question directly:
    "What planter are you using, and what speed were you operating at on these fields?"
    before concluding anything about speed effects.

    Close by setting expectations for next steps:
    "Once the [planter issue / seed selection / field condition] is addressed, run the YP1K
    analysis again on next season's data. With corrected emergence, the rate recommendations
    will be clean and actionable."
  </communication>

  <follow_up>
    After presenting the emergence investigation findings, ask targeted questions based on
    the pattern:

    For planter_issue pattern:
      "When was the planter meter last calibrated?"
      "Has the seed disk been inspected this season?"
      "Is this a high-speed planter (SpeedTube, ExactEmerge, or similar)? If so, at what
      speed were these fields planted?"
      "Was there any row-unit skip or bounce noticed during planting?"

    For mixed pattern (hybrid-specific):
      "Were [affected hybrids] planted at a different time or in different field conditions
      than the hybrids that emerged well?"
      "Did [affected hybrids] have a different seed treatment package?"
      "What were the soil temperatures at planting for the affected versus unaffected fields?"

    For drainage-correlated gaps:
      "Were the [poorly/somewhat poorly] drained fields planted earlier in the spring when
      soils were still cold?"
      "Is there tile drainage in those fields, and is it functioning?"

    Do not ask all of these questions at once. Read the data first, identify the most likely
    explanation, and ask the one or two questions that would confirm or rule it out.
  </follow_up>

</skill>
