<skill name="yp1k" version="6">

  <purpose>
    Analyze seeding rate optimization using the Yield Per 1,000 plants (YP1K) diagnostic.
    YP1K measures how hard each plant is working: YP1K = Harvest Yield / (Emerged Stand / 1,000).
    A high YP1K means plants are maximized and the field has room for more. A low YP1K means
    plants are competing with each other.

    Use this skill when a grower asks about seeding rates, population optimization, whether they
    are over- or under-seeded, or how their seed program is performing relative to yield outcomes.

    The skill is two-stage by design. Stage 1 checks emergence quality before any rate recommendation
    is made. Adding seed onto a field with a planter problem is the wrong answer — Stage 1 enforces
    that discipline. Stage 2 computes YP1K per hybrid and generates rate adjustment recommendations.

    Do not skip Stage 1. Do not shortcut to rate recommendations without reviewing emergence first.
    This is the invariant the whole workflow depends on.
  </purpose>

  <interpretation>

    <stage name="emergence" label="Stage 1 — Emergence Diagnostic">
      The analyze step (step 2) runs compute_yp1k which adds an emerged_stand column and a gap
      column. Gap = planting_population - emerged_stand. The detect_gap_pattern primitive
      classifies the operation-wide pattern.

      Read the gap_result output from step 2 to determine severity and pattern before reading
      any YP1K numbers.

      Corn emergence gap thresholds:
        Normal    — gap below 1,000 seeds/ac: Proceed to Stage 2 without caveats.
        Minor     — gap 1,000 to 2,000: Elevated. Note and monitor. Proceed.
        Warning   — gap 2,000 to 3,000: Significant. Investigate before recommending rate changes.
        Critical  — gap above 3,000: Serious. Fix the root cause first. Do not recommend rate changes.

      Soybean emergence gap thresholds:
        Normal    — gap below 5,000 seeds/ac: Proceed to Stage 2 without caveats.
        Minor     — gap 5,000 to 10,000: Elevated. Note and monitor. Proceed.
        Warning   — gap 10,000 to 15,000: Significant. Investigate before recommending rate changes.
        Critical  — gap above 15,000: Serious. Fix the root cause first. Do not recommend rate changes.

      Pattern interpretation (from detect_gap_pattern):
        planter_issue — more than 80% of fields and zones have elevated gaps. The problem is
          uniform across all hybrids. This is a planter delivery problem, not a hybrid or
          environment problem. Do not recommend rate changes. Investigate the planter.
        mixed — 30 to 80% of fields have elevated gaps. Some hybrids or fields are affected.
          Likely seed-environment interaction. Exclude affected hybrids from rate recommendations.
          Present YP1K analysis for the unaffected hybrids.
        localized — fewer than 30% of fields have elevated gaps. Most data is valid. Proceed
          to Stage 2 with a light note about the isolated outliers.

      When gap is critical and pattern is planter_issue: stop the analysis at Stage 1. Tell
      the grower what was found, explain why rate recommendations cannot be made on top of a
      delivery problem, and direct them to investigate the planter before next season. The
      emergence investigation reference plan (references/emergence) provides the deeper framework.

      When gap is critical and pattern is mixed: proceed to Stage 2 but exclude the affected
      hybrids from rate recommendations. Flag them separately with a note.

      When gap is at warning level: proceed to Stage 2 with an explicit caveat that the emergence
      data has uncertainty and recommendations should be monitored before committing to changes.
    </stage>

    <stage name="yp1k" label="Stage 2 — YP1K Rate Optimization">
      After emergence clears the gate, interpret the YP1K values per hybrid from the step 2
      output. Always evaluate at the hybrid level first. The operation-level overall YP1K is a
      summary — rate changes must be hybrid-specific.

      Corn YP1K decision table:
        Above 8.5         — Significantly under-seeded. Add 4,000 to 5,000 seeds/ac.
        8.0 to 8.4        — Under-seeded. Add 3,000 to 4,000 seeds/ac.
        7.5 to 7.9        — Slightly under-seeded. Add 1,000 to 2,000 seeds/ac.
        7.0 to 7.5        — Optimal. Hold current rate.
        6.5 to 6.9        — Slightly over-seeded. Reduce 1,000 to 2,000 seeds/ac.
        Below 6.5         — Over-seeded. Reduce 2,000 to 3,000 seeds/ac.

      Soybean YP1K decision table:
        Above 0.65        — Significantly under-seeded. Add 15,000 to 20,000 seeds/ac.
        0.55 to 0.65      — Under-seeded. Add 10,000 to 15,000 seeds/ac.
        0.50 to 0.55      — Slightly under-seeded. Add 5,000 to 10,000 seeds/ac.
        0.45 to 0.50      — Optimal. Hold current rate.
        0.40 to 0.45      — Slightly over-seeded. Reduce 5,000 to 10,000 seeds/ac.
        Below 0.40        — Over-seeded. Reduce 10,000 to 15,000 seeds/ac.

      Field-type target adjustment — the optimal band shifts by field quality:
        Best ground       — Corn YP1K 7.0 to 7.25. Soil can support competition.
        Average ground    — Corn YP1K 7.25 to 7.5. Balanced risk and reward.
        Droughty ground   — Corn YP1K 7.5 to 8.0. Buffer against dry-year stress.
        Irrigated         — Corn YP1K 6.8 to 7.0. Water removes competition constraint.
      Soybeans shift similarly: adjust the optimal band by plus or minus 0.03 to 0.05 for
      field type. A corn YP1K of 7.6 on droughty ground is within target for that field type
      even though the standard table labels it slightly_under. Always apply field-type context.

      Multi-year stability caveat: a single year's YP1K, especially in a drought year, is not
      sufficient justification for a permanent rate change. In a drought year yield drops more
      than stand count, inflating YP1K even at the correct population. Do not recommend a
      permanent rate reduction from a single stress-year observation. Require at least two
      seasons of data or cross-reference with the aggregate database.

      The render step (step 3) composes the shared YP1K UI templates directly from the
      workspace table. It produces the same heatmaps, field summary, economics, placement,
      and agronomics surfaces the user sees in the panel. Those same template parts can be
      rendered independently in other skills; this skill just uses the full dashboard shape.
      The step 2 text output is for the agent's reasoning and for hook metadata only.
    </stage>

  </interpretation>

  <communication>
    Lead with the finding. Do not bury the headline in caveats. State the overall YP1K first,
    then the hybrid breakdown, then the adjustments.

    Use economic framing to make recommendations concrete, but follow these rules:
      Never hard-code returns. Seed cost and grain price change every year. Say "at illustrative
      assumptions" or "at your seed cost" rather than stating a guaranteed dollar figure.
      The directional logic is what matters — under-seeding costs yield, over-seeding wastes seed.
      Always show both sides of the economic case: seed cost delta AND expected yield effect.
      Scale to the operation. A $12/ac finding on 500 acres is $6,000 — use the actual acreage.

    Never recommend a rate change without checking emergence first. The two-stage structure
    is the only credible path. If asked for a quick rate recommendation before emergence is
    reviewed, decline politely and explain why the gate exists.

    Never present the same rate change for all fields. Some fields are best ground that
    supports higher population; others are droughty and benefit from fewer plants. Segment
    before prescribing.

    Never compare a grower's YP1K to their neighbor's operation. The data tells each farmer
    what is right for their fields — not what is right for someone else's soils and hybrids.

    Never recommend a population change based on a single stress year's data without flagging
    the caveat explicitly.

    When all hybrids are optimal, say so plainly and shift the conversation. "Your rates are
    dialed in. No changes recommended. Here is what that means for next season." Do not
    manufacture urgency where none exists.

    When emergence is critical, be direct and specific: state the gap number, name the pattern,
    explain the cause, and give the grower a concrete next step. Do not say "I found a problem"
    without telling them what it is and what to do about it.
  </communication>

  <follow_up>
    After presenting findings, the conversation branches based on what was found:

    If emergence is critical and pattern is planter_issue:
      Do not proceed to rate recommendations. Direct the grower toward planter investigation.
      Say: "Before we look at seeding rates, I want to flag something. Across your [crop_type]
      fields, we are seeing an emergence gap of [X,XXX] seeds/acre — that is [severity]. This
      pattern is consistent across all your hybrids, which points to the planter rather than
      any specific seed. Adding more seed right now would go through the same planter at the
      same reduced rate. I would recommend getting the planter checked before next season and
      then running this analysis again on corrected data."
      The hooks section automatically fires the emergence reference plan in this case.

    If under-seeded patterns found (most hybrids above target YP1K):
      Present the hybrid-by-hybrid breakdown from the step 2 output and the dashboard (step 3).
      Offer to generate field-level prescriptions: "I can generate zone-specific rate
      prescriptions with recommended populations by drainage class. Want me to run that?"

    If over-seeded patterns found (most hybrids below target YP1K):
      Present the economics of the seed cost savings first. Check whether this is a drought-year
      artifact before recommending a permanent rate cut.

    If mixed results (some hybrids optimal, some not):
      Segment by field type and drainage class before presenting recommendations. A hybrid
      at YP1K 7.6 on droughty ground is in target for that field type — do not apply the
      standard table without field-type context.

    If all hybrids are optimal:
      Present the "dialed in" summary. Check whether certain fields are at the edges of the
      optimal band and whether those match their expected field type. Shift the conversation
      to other variables: hybrid selection, fertility, drainage.
  </follow_up>

  <references>
    <plan name="emergence"
          path="references/emergence"
          trigger="emergence gap critical — gap above corn 3,000 or soy 15,000 seeds/ac, with planter_issue pattern"
          description="Deeper emergence investigation: identifies which fields and hybrids are most affected, checks for planting speed effects (high-speed planter context), correlates gap with drainage class and field conditions, builds the case for a planter audit." />
    <plan name="placement"
          path="references/placement"
          trigger="under-seeded hybrids detected — one or more hybrids above the optimal YP1K range with valid emergence"
          description="Field-level prescription generation: queries aggregate database for hybrid-specific optimal rates by drainage class, maps prescriptions to field zones, builds variable-rate prescription table exportable as ISOXML." />
  </references>

</skill>
