<skill name="zone-prescription" version="1">
  <purpose>
    Generate variable-rate prescriptions for seed, nitrogen, and/or fertilizer
    with zone-level map visualization and downloadable ISOXML files.

    Use when: grower wants variable-rate prescriptions, asks to optimize
    seeding/nitrogen/fertilizer rates by zone, needs a prescription file for
    equipment (John Deere Operations Center, Climate FieldView, etc.), or
    wants to see rate recommendations on a map.
  </purpose>

  <parameters>
    <param name="prescription_types" required="true">
      Comma-separated list of prescription types to generate.
      Options: seed, nitrogen, fertilizer.
      Ask the user which type(s) they want. If unclear, default to "seed".
      Multiple types can be combined: "seed,nitrogen" generates both.
    </param>
    <param name="year" required="true">Crop year to analyze.</param>
    <param name="crop_type" required="true">"corn" or "soybeans"</param>
    <param name="company_id" required="true">
      Company ID. REQUIRED for performance — without it the query scans
      the entire database and will timeout.
    </param>
    <param name="field_name" required="false">
      Optional filter to a single field. Omit for all fields in the company.
    </param>
  </parameters>

  <interpretation>
    <stage name="seed">
      Seeding rate prescriptions use drainage-stratified yield response data.
      For each drainage class, the population bucket with the highest
      weighted-average yield becomes the recommended rate. This is empirical,
      not theoretical — derived from THIS operation's actual data.

      Zones with rate change less than 500 seeds/ac (corn) or 3,000 seeds/ac
      (soybeans) are treated as "on target."
    </stage>

    <stage name="nitrogen">
      Nitrogen prescriptions use application history correlated with yield
      response. Zones are grouped by soil productivity tier and drainage class.
      The N rate that produced peak yield in each group becomes the recommendation.
      If no application data exists, soil-productivity-based defaults are used.
    </stage>

    <stage name="fertilizer">
      Fertilizer prescriptions use yield-based nutrient removal rates adjusted
      by soil productivity. Higher-yielding zones need more maintenance
      fertility. Soil test data (if available) adjusts recommendations by
      current nutrient levels.
    </stage>
  </interpretation>

  <communication>
    Present results as actionable:
    "I've generated [type] prescriptions for your [crop]. The zone map shows
    recommended rates across [N] zones ([M] acres). The ISOXML file is ready
    to download and load into your planter/applicator display."

    When multiple prescription types are combined:
    "I've generated seed and nitrogen prescriptions. Use the layer switcher
    on the zone map to toggle between seeding rate and N rate views. Both
    prescriptions are included in the download file."

    If most zones show no change from current rates, frame positively:
    "Your current rates are well-matched. Only [X] zones have meaningful
    adjustments — the rest are on target."

    Never present rates as universal truth — they're derived from this
    operation's specific data and conditions.
  </communication>

  <follow_up>
    After prescription generation, offer:
    - "Want me to run the YP1K analysis for a deeper look at hybrid-level
      seeding rate efficiency?"
    - "Should I export this as a shapefile for use in other GIS tools?"
    - "Want to see how these rates compare to last year's application?"
    - "You can fork this skill and customize the rate logic for your
      specific agronomic approach — just ask me to help you modify it."
  </follow_up>
</skill>
